Hawa Abdi: Many people -- 20 years for Somalia --
حواء عبدي: الكثير من الناس -- 20 سنة للصومال--
[were] fighting.
كانوا يقاتلون.
So there was no job, no food.
بسبب عدم توفر العمل، والطعام.
Children, most of them,
وأصبح معظم الأطفال،
became very malnourished, like this.
يعانون من سوء التغذية مثل هذا.
Deqo Mohamed: So as you know,
ديكو: إذاً كما تعلمون،
always in a civil war,
دائماً في الحروب الأهلية،
the ones affected most [are] the women and children.
أكثر من يتأثر بها هم النساء والأطفال.
So our patients are women and children.
لذا فمرضانا هم النساء والأطفال.
And they are in our backyard.
وهم دائماً في فناء منزلنا الخلفي.
It's our home. We welcome them.
إنه بيتنا، ونحن نرحب بهم.
That's the camp that we have in now
هذا هو معسكرنا وهم معنا الآن
90,000 people,
90 ألف شخص،
where 75 percent of them are women and children.
75 بالمائة منهم نساء وأطفال.
Pat Mitchell: And this is your hospital. This is the inside.
بات ميتشل: وهذا هو مستشفاكم. هذا بالداخل.
HA: We are doing C-sections and different operations
حواء: نحن نقوم بعمليات ولادة قيصرية وعمليات مختلفة
because people need some help.
لأن الناس بحاجة للمساعدة.
There is no government to protect them.
لا توجد حكومة تقوم بحمايتهم.
DM: Every morning we have about 400 patients,
دوكو: كل صباح نستقبل حوالي 400 مريضاً،
maybe more or less.
ربما يزيد أو يقل.
But sometimes we are only five doctors
لكن بعض الأحيان نحن خمس أطباء فقط
and 16 nurses,
و16 ممرضة،
and we are physically getting exhausted to see all of them.
ونصبح منهكين جسدياً لفحصهم جميعاً.
But we take the severe ones,
لكننا نأخذ من فحصناهم،
and we reschedule the other ones the next day.
ونقوم بمقابلة البقية في اليوم التالي.
It is very tough.
إنه عملٌ مضني.
And as you can see, it's the women who are carrying the children;
وكما ترون، فالنساء هن من يحملن الأطفال،
it's the women who come into the hospitals;
والنساء هنّ من يأتين إلى المستشفى،
it's the women [are] building the houses.
والنساء هنّ من يبنين المنازل.
That's their house.
ذلك منزلهن.
And we have a school. This is our bright --
ولدينا مدرسة. هذا مصدر فخرنا--
we opened [in the] last two years [an] elementary school
لقد إفتتحنا مدرسة إبتدائية في العامين الماضيين
where we have 850 children,
ولدينا 850 تلميذاً،
and the majority are women and girls.
والأغلبية هن النساء والبنات.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
PM: And the doctors have some very big rules
بات: ولدى الأطباء بعض القوانين الكبيرة
about who can get treated at the clinic.
حول من يُعالج في العيادة.
Would you explain the rules for admission?
هلّا شرحتي لهم القوانين للدخول؟
HA: The people who are coming to us,
حواء: الناس الذين يأتون إلينا،
we are welcoming.
نحن نرحب بهم.
We are sharing with them
نحن نتقاسم معهم
whatever we have.
كل ما لدينا.
But there are only two rules.
لكن هناك قانونين.
First rule:
القانون الأول:
there is no clan distinguished and political division
لا نقبل بأي تقسيم عشائري أو سياسي
in Somali society.
في المجتمع الصومالي.
[Whomever] makes those things we throw out.
كل من يخرق ذلك القانون نقوم بطرده خارجاً.
The second:
القانون الثاني:
no man can beat his wife.
لا يضرب أي رجل زوجته.
If he beat,
إذا قام بضربها،
we will put [him] in jail,
سنقوم بسجنه،
and we will call the eldest people.
وننادي المشايخ الأكبر سناً.
Until they identify this case,
حتى يتعرفوا على هذه الحالة،
we'll never release him.
ولا نطلق سراحه مطلقاً.
That's our two rules.
ذلك هو قانوننا الثاني.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The other thing that I have realized,
الشئ الثاني الذي أدركته،
that the woman is the most strong person
هو أن النساء هن الأكثر قوة
all over the world.
في كل أنحاء العالم.
Because the last 20 years,
لأنه خلال ال 20 سنة الماضية
the Somali woman has stood up.
قاومت المرأة الصومالية.
They were the leaders,
لقد كانوا هن القادة،
and we are the leaders
ونحن قادة
of our community
مجتمعاتنا
and the hope of our future generations.
والأمل لمستقبل الأجيال.
We are not just the helpless
نحن ليس نفتقد للمساعدة
and the victims of the civil war.
وضحايا الحرب الأهلية
We can reconcile.
بل نحن نستطيع التصالح
We can do everything.
يمكننا فعل أي شئ.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
DM: As my mother said, we are the future hope,
دوكو: كما قالت أمي، نحن أمل المستقبل،
and the men are only killing in Somalia.
والرجال يقتلون فقط في الصومال.
So we came up with these two rules.
ولذا توصلنا لهذين القانونين.
In a camp with 90,000 people,
وفي معسكر مع 90 ألف نسمة،
you have to come up with some rules or there is going to be some fights.
ينبغي أن تتوصل لقوانين أو يتحول هذا إلى نوع من الصراع.
So there is no clan division,
لهذا السبب رفضنا التقسيمات العشائرية
and no man can beat his wife.
وأن لا يضرب رجل زوجته.
And we have a little storage room
ولدينا غرفة مخزن صغيرة
where we converted a jail.
حيث قمنا بتحويلها إلى سجن.
So if you beat your wife, you're going to be there.
بحيث اذا ضربت زوجتك، سينتهي بك الحال هناك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So empowering the women and giving the opportunity --
وبذا نقوم بتمكين النساء وإعطائهن الفرصة --
we are there for them. They are not alone for this.
ونحن هناك من أجلهن. وليسوا وحدهن في ذلك الأمر.
PM: You're running a medical clinic.
بات: أنتم تديرون عيادة طبية.
It brought much, much needed medical care
لقد قدمت الكثير والكثير من الرعاية الطبية المطلوبة
to people who wouldn't get it.
لأناس لم يكونوا ليحصلوا عليها.
You're also running a civil society.
ونحن كذلك ندير مجتمعاً مدنياً.
You've created your own rules,
وقد أقمنا قوانيننا الخاصة بنا
in which women and children
التي فيها النساء والأطفال
are getting a different sense of security.
يحصلون على إحساس مختلف من الطمأنينة والأمن.
Talk to me about your decision, Dr. Abdi,
أخبريني عن قرارك، د. عبدي،
and your decision, Dr. Mohamed,
وعن قرارك د. محمد،
to work together --
للعمل سوياً --
for you to become a doctor
بالنسبة لك لتصبحي طبيبة
and to work with your mother in these circumstances.
وأن تعملي مع والدتك في مثل هذه الظروف.
HA: My age --
حواء: عُمري --
because I was born in 1947 --
لأنني مولودة عام 1947 --
we were having, at that time,
وكان لدينا في ذلك الوقت،
government, law and order.
حكومة وقانون ونظام.
But one day, I went to the hospital --
لكن في أحد الأيام، ذهبت للمستشفى --
my mother was sick --
وكانت والدتي مريضة --
and I saw the hospital, how they [were] treating the doctors,
وقد رأيت المستشفى، وكيف كانوا يعاملون الأطباء،
how they [are] committed
وكيف أنهم ملتزمون
to help the sick people.
بمساعدة المرضى.
I admired them,
وقد إحترمتهم،
and I decided to become a doctor.
وقررت أن أصبح طبيبة.
My mother died, unfortunately,
بكل أسف توفيت والدتي،
when I was 12 years [old].
عندما بلغت عمر 12.
Then my father allowed me
ثم سمح لي والدي
to proceed [with] my hope.
بالمواصلة في تحقيق حلمي.
My mother died
توفيت والدتي
in [a] gynecology complication,
بتعقيدات طبية متعلقة بالنساء،
so I decided to become
ولذا قررت أن أصبح
a gynecology specialist.
متخصصة نساء.
That's why I became a doctor.
ولهذا أصبحت طبيبة.
So Dr. Deqo has to explain.
إذاً حان وقت د. دوكو.
DM: For me, my mother was preparing [me] when I was a child
دوكو: بالنسبة لي، كانت والدتي ترعاني وأنا طفلة
to become a doctor, but I really didn't want to.
لأصبح طبيبة، لكني لم أحب ذلك حقاً.
Maybe I should become an historian,
ربما كان عليّ أن أصبح عالمة تاريخ
or maybe a reporter.
أو ربما صحفية.
I loved it, but it didn't work.
لقد أحببت ذلك، لكني لم أنجح
When the war broke out -- civil war --
وعندما بدأت الحرب الأهلية
I saw how my mother was helping
رأيت أمي تقوم بالمساعدة
and how she really needed the help,
وكيف أنها أرادت المساعدة
and how the care is essential to the woman
وكيف أن الرعاية الصحية أساسية للنساء
to be a woman doctor in Somalia
ولأن تكون طبيبة في الصومال
and help the women and children.
وتساعد النساء والأطفال.
And I thought, maybe I can be a reporter and doctor gynecologist.
ففكرت، ربما أستطيع أن أكون صحافية وطبيبة نساء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I went to Russia, and my mother also,
لذا ذهبت إلى روسيا، وكذلك والدتي
[during the] time of [the] Soviet Union.
على أيام الإتحاد السوفيتي.
So some of our character,
ولذا فجانب من شخصيتنا
maybe we will come with a strong Soviet background of training.
جاء ربما من خلفية قوية وتدريب سوفيتي ممتاز.
So that's how I decided [to do] the same.
هكذا قررت أن أفعل نفس الشئ وأصبح طبيبة.
My sister was different.
كانت أختي مختلفة
She's here. She's also a doctor.
وهي هنا. وهي أيضاً طبيبة.
She graduated in Russia also.
وقد تخرجت من روسيا أيضاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And to go back and to work with our mother
ودافع العودة وأعمل مع والدتنا
is just what we saw in the civil war --
هو ما شهدناه خلال الحرب الأهلية--
when I was 16, and my sister was 11,
عندما كان عمري 16 وأختي عمرها 11
when the civil war broke out.
عندما أندلعت الحرب.
So it was the need and the people we saw
فالأمر متعلق بالإحتياج... والناس الذين رأيناهم
in the early '90s --
في بواكير التسعينيات،
that's what made us go back
هذا ما دعانا للرجوع
and work for them.
والعمل من أجلهم.
PM: So what is the biggest challenge
بات: إذاً ما هو أكبر تحدي
working, mother and daughter,
العمل مع والدتك وأختك،
in such dangerous
في مثل هذه الظروف
and sometimes scary situations?
الخطرة وبعض الأحيان المخيفة؟
HA: Yes, I was working in a tough situation,
حواء: نعم، كنت أعمل في أوضاع قاسية،
very dangerous.
خطيرة للغاية.
And when I saw the people who needed me,
وعندما رأيت الناس المحتاجين لمساعدتي،
I was staying with them to help,
كنت أبقى لمساعدتهم،
because I [could] do something for them.
لأن بإستطاعتي فعل شئ من أجلهم.
Most people fled abroad.
معظم الناس هاجر إلى الخارج.
But I remained with those people,
لكني بقيت مع أؤلئك الناس،
and I was trying to do something --
وكنت أحاول فعل شئ --
[any] little thing I [could] do.
أقل شئ أستطيع فعله.
I succeeded in my place.
وقد نجحت في مكاني.
Now my place is 90,000 people
ويحوي مكاني الآن 90 ألف شخص
who are respecting each other,
يقومون باحترام بعضهم البعض
who are not fighting.
بدون أي خلافات.
But we try to stand on our feet,
لكننا نحاول الوقوف على أقدامنا،
to do something, little things, we can for our people.
لفعل شئ صغير، يمكننا فعله لصالح شعبنا.
And I'm thankful for my daughters.
وأنا شاكرة لأبنتي.
When they come to me,
عندما جاءوا إليّ
they help me to treat the people,
لقد ساعدوني في علاج المرضى،
to help.
من أجل المساعدة.
They do everything for them.
وقد فعلوا كل شئ من أجلهم.
They have done what I desire to do for them.
وقد فعلوا ما طلبته منهم.
PM: What's the best part
بات: ما هو أفضل جزء
of working with your mother,
في العمل مع والدتك
and the most challenging part for you?
وأكثر الأجزاء صعوبة بالنسبة لك؟
DM: She's very tough; it's most challenging.
دوكو: إنها صعبة جداً، وهذا أكثر تحدي.
She always expects us to do more.
إنها تتوقع منا فعل المزيد دائماً.
And really when you think [you] cannot do it,
وعندما تحس أنك لا تستطيع فعل ذلك،
she will push you, and I can do it.
تقوم بتشجيعك، وأستطيع فعل ذلك.
That's the best part.
هذا هو أفضل جزء.
She shows us, trains us how to do
وهي تقوم بتدريبنا
and how to be better [people]
كيف نصبح بشراً أفضل
and how to do long hours in surgery --
وكيف نأخذ وقت أطول في الجراحة --
300 patients per day,
300 مريض يومياً،
10, 20 surgeries,
10 إلى 20 جراحة،
and still you have to manage the camp --
ويتعين عليك إدارة المعسكر في نفس الوقت--
that's how she trains us.
هكذا تقوم بتدريبنا.
It is not like beautiful offices here,
الأمر ليس مكاتب جميلة هنا،
20 patients, you're tired.
20 مريضاً، وأنت منهكة.
You see 300 patients, 20 surgeries
تقابلين 300 مريضاً، وتقومين ب 20 جراحة
and 90,000 people to manage.
وعليك إدارة 90 ألف شخص.
PM: But you do it for good reasons.
بات: لكنك تقومين بذلك لأسباب رائعة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Wait. Wait.
أنتظروا.
HA: Thank you.
حواء: شكراً لكم.
DM: Thank you.
دوكو: شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
HA: Thank you very much. DM: Thank you very much.
حواء: شكراً جزيلاً لكم. (دوكو: شكراً جزيلاً لكم.)